"What’s the Ideal BMI and Waist Size?"
We seem to have become inured
to the mortal threat of obesity.
If you go back in the medical
literature a half century or so
when obesity wasn’t
just run-of-the-mill,
the descriptions are
much more grim:
“Obesity is always tragic, and
its hazards are terrifying.”
But it’s not just obesity.
Of the 4 million deaths every year
attributed to excess body fat,
nearly 40% of the victims
are just overweight, not obese.
According to two famous
Harvard studies, weight gain
of as little as 11 pounds from
early adulthood through middle age
increases the risk of
major chronic diseases,
such as diabetes, cardiovascular
disease, and cancer.
The flipside, though, is
that even modest weight loss
can have major health benefits.
What’s the optimal BMI?
The largest studies in the
United States and around the world
found that having a normal body
mass index, a BMI from 20 to 25,
is associated with
the longest lifespan.
Put all the best available
studies with the longest
follow-up together and that
can be narrowed down even further
to a BMI of 20 to 22.
That would be about
between 124 to 136 pounds for
someone who stands five-foot-six.
You can pause the video
here to use this unisex chart
to see what your optimal weight
might be based on your height.
But, even within a normal BMI,
the risk of developing
chronic diseases, such as
type 2 diabetes, heart disease,
and several types of cancer starts
to rise towards the upper end,
even starting as low as a BMI of 21.
A BMI of 18.5 and 24.5 are both
considered within the normal range,
but a BMI of 24.5 may
be associated with twice
the heart disease risk compared 18.5.
Look at this diabetes graph
among women, a five-fold difference
in diabetes rates all within
the so-called ideal range under 25.
Just as there are gradations
of risk within a normal BMI range,
there is a spectrum within obesity.
Class III obesity, a BMI
over 40, can be associated
with the loss of a decade of life or more.
At a BMI greater than 45,
such as a five-foot-six person
at 280 pounds, life
expectancy may shrink
to that of a cigarette smoker.
There are, however,
so-called “obesity skeptics”
that argue that the health
consequences of obesity are unclear
or even greatly exaggerated.
They are a motley bunch,
ranging from feminists,
queer theorists, and new ageists
to “far right wing, pro-gun,
pro-America websites
where the idea [is] that
obesity alarmists are nanny-state
communists who simply want
to stop us from having fun….”
Unlike activists who,
for example, organized to raise
consciousness and stamp
out the AIDS epidemic,
the size acceptance movement
appears to have the opposite goal,
rallying for less public awareness
and treatment of the problem.
(They do have good slogans though:
“We’re here, we’re spheres,
get used to it!”)
I’m all for fighting size
stigma and discrimination—
I have a whole section on
weight stigma in my new book—
but the adverse health
consequences of obesity
are an established scientific fact.
Can’t you be fat but fit?
In a study of more
than 600 centenarians
(those living over 100)
only about 1% of the women
and not a single one
of the men were obese.
But there does appear to be a
rare subgroup of obese individuals
who don’t suffer the
typical metabolic costs
such as high blood
pressure and cholesterol.
This raises the possibility that
there may be such thing as
“benign obesity” or “healthy obesity.”
It may just be a matter of time, though,
before the risk factors develop.
And even if they don’t,
followed long enough,
even quote-unquote “metabolically
healthy” obese individuals
are at increased risk of
diabetes, and fatty liver disease
and cardiovascular
events such as heart attacks,
and/or premature death.
Bottom line: there
is strong evidence
that so-called “healthy
obesity” is a myth.
Many “fat-activists” try to
downplay the risks of obesity,
even as they may be among
the epidemic’s greatest victims.
Lynn McAfee is the
director of medical advocacy
for the Council on Size
and Weight Discrimination
and routinely takes
part in obesity conferences
and government panels on obesity.
“I’m not actually particularly
that interested in [health],”
she is quoted as saying,
“and God I hate science.”
There was a book originally published in
the '80s, and then repeatedly republished,
entitled "DIETING MAKES YOU FAT".
Since most people who lose
weight go on to regain it,
the concern is that there may
be adverse health consequences
of so-called yo-yo dieting.
This idea emerged from
animal studies that showed,
for example, detrimental effects of
starving and refeeding obese rats.
This captured the media's attention,
leading to a pervasive common belief
about the dangers of weight cycling,
discouraging people from even trying.
Even the animal data is
inconclusive though.
For example, weight cycling
mice makes them live longer.
Most importantly though, a review
of the human data concluded
that evidence for an adverse effect
of weight cycling appears sparse,
if it exists at all.
Bottom line:
Yo-Yo Dieting is Better Than None.
Ideally, we'd get down to a BMI of 20
to 22, but body mass index doesn't
take the composition of the
weight into account. For example,
bodybuilders are heavy for their
height, but can be extremely lean.
The gold standard measure of
obesity is percentage body fat,
but an accurate calculation can
be complicated and expensive.
All you need to measure
BMI is height and weight,
but it may underestimate
the true prevalence of obesity.
The World Health
Organization defines obesity
as a body fat percentage over
25% in men or 35% in women.
At a BMI of 25, which is
considered just barely overweight,
body fat percentages in a representative
US sample of adults varied between
14% and 35% in men, and
26% and 43% in women.
So you could be normal
weight but actually obese.
Using the BMI cutoff for obesity only
about 1 in 5 Americans were obese
back in the 90's, but based on
their body fat, the true proportion
even back then was closer to 50%.
Half of America is not just
overweight, but obese.
So just using BMI, doctors may
misclassify more than half
of obese individuals as being just
overweight or even normal weight
and miss an opportunity to intervene.
The important thing is not the label,
though, but the health consequences.
Ironically, BMI appears to
be an even better predictor
of cardiovascular disease death
than percentage body fat.
I mean, that suggests that excess
weight from any source, fat or lean,
may not be healthy in the long run.
The lifespan of bodybuilders
does seem to be cut short.
They have about a third higher mortality
rate than the general population.
The average age of death was around
48 years old, but this may well be due
in part to the toxic effects
of anabolic steroids on the heart.
Pre-eminent nutritional physiologist Ancel
Keys (after which K-rations were named)
suggested the mirror method.
If you really want to know
whether you are obese,
just undress and look
at yourself in the mirror.
Don't worry about our fancy
laboratory measurements; you'll know!
All fat is not the same, though.
There is the pinchable superficial flab
that you may see
jiggling about your body,
but then there's the riskier, deeper
visceral fat which coils around
and infiltrates
your internal organs.
Measuring BMI is simple, cheap, and
effective, but does not take into account
the distribution of fat on the body,
whereas waist circumference
can provide a measure
of the deep underlying belly fat.
Both BMI and waist circumference can
be used to predict the risk of death
due to excess body fat, but even
at the same BMI there appears to
be nearly a straight-line increase in
mortality risk with widening waistline.
Someone with normal-weight
central obesity, meaning someone
not even overweight according to BMI,
but fat around the middle may
have up to twice the risk of dying
compared to even someone who's obese
according to their height and weight.
This is why the current
recommendations recommend
measuring both: BMI
and waist circumference.
This may be especially important for
older women who lose approximately
13 pounds of bone and muscle
as they age from 25 to 65,
while quadrupling their visceral fat
stores (men tend to only double).
So even if a woman doesn't gain any
weight based on the bathroom scale,
she may be gaining fat.
What's the waistline cut-off?
Increased risk of
metabolic complications
start at an abdominal circumference
of 31.5" in women, and 37" in most men,
though closer to 35.5" for South Asian,
Chinese, and Japanese men.
The benchmark for substantially
increased risk starts
at about 34.5" for women,
and 40" for men.
Once you get over an abdominal
circumference of about 43" in men,
mortality rates shoot up
about 50%, compared to men
with 8-inch-smaller stomachs.
And women suffer 80% greater mortality
risk at 37.5" compared to 27.5".
The reading of a measuring tape may
translate into years off one's lifespan.
The good news is the riskiest
fat is the easiest to lose.
Your body appears smart
enough to preferentially shed
the villainous visceral fat first.
Although it may take losing
as much as 20% of your
weight to realize significant
improvements in quality
of life for most individuals
with severe obesity, your disease
risk drops almost immediately.
At 3% weight loss (just like 6 pounds
for someone weighing 200 pounds)
your blood sugar control and
triglycerides start to get better.
At 5%, your blood pressure
and cholesterol improve.
Just a 5% weight loss (about 10
pounds for someone starting at 200)
may cut your risk of
developing diabetes in half.